A Finding Aid to the Galerie Chalette Records, 1916-1999, bulk 1939-1994, in the Archives of American Art AAA.galechal
Archives of American Art
- Personal Papers of Arthur and Madeleine Chalette Lejwa, 1925-1999; Series 7; 3.7 Linear feet Boxes 17-21, 25
  - Printed Materials, 1929-1999; 7.5
    - Clippings, Arthur Lejwa, 1943-1951 (Box 20, Folder 6-8)
    - Clippings, Arthur Lejwa, 1972-1973 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, Various, 1936-1995 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Displaced Jews, 1946-1947 (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - Event Invitations and Programs, 1943-1951 (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - The Israel Museum, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - The Jerusalem Foundation, 1969-1974, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - Maps, 1950 (Box 20, Folder 16)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 20, Folder 17)
    - Patent Application, 1942 (Box 20, Folder 18)
    - Posters, 1946 (Box 20, Folder 19)
    - Professional Papers of Arthur Lejwa, 1947-1951 (Box 20, Folder 20)
    - Project Notebook, 1947 (Box 20, Folder 21)
    - Publications (Box 20)
      - Art-related, 1948, 1974-1987 (Box 20, Folder 22)
      - Arthur Lejwa, 1929-1932 (Box 20, Folder 23)
      - Scientific, 1938-1942 (Box 20, Folder 24)
      - Scientific, 1943-1944 (Box 20, Folder 25)
      - Scientific, 1946-1948 (Box 20, Folder 26)
      - Scientific, 1949-1960 (Box 20, Folder 27)
      - Various, 1951, 1971 (Box 20, Folder 28)
    - Robert Gould Research Foundation, 1946-1947 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - War Ration Book, circa 1943 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Writings, undated (Box 21, Folder 3)
- Motion Picture Film, Audio, and Video Recordings, circa 1950s-1995; Series 8; 2.7 Linear feet Boxes 21-23, 26
  This series contains 58 film reels, 7 video recordings, and 61 audio recordings of broadcasts, lectures, interviews, exhibitions and personal travels. The bulk of this series is from the 2005 collection addition and is minimally processed.
  Subseries 8.1: Audio Recordings, 1964-1994
  Subseries 8.2: Film and Video Recordings, circa 1950s-1995
  - Audio Recordings, 1964-1994; 8.1
    This subseries contains 61 sound recordings, including 12 sound tape reels (1/4"), 42 sound cassettes, 4 microcassettes, and 3 1/4" minifon sound cassettes. Recordings are of broadcasts, lectures, interviews, and readings related to artists, exhibits, and Madeleine Lejwa's travels. The folder titles are based on the labeling of the recorded media. There are no transcripts of the audio recordings. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by subject or last name. The cassette tapes are filed together in the box container.
    - Anatolia Trip, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 21)
    - Jean Arp (Box 21)
      - Marguerite Arp Guggenheim Speech, 1968; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
      - John Gilbert, undated; 2 sound tape reels (Box 21)
      - Julie Copeland with Madeleine Chalette Lejwa, Arp Exhibit, undated; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
      - Installation at NYU Gould Plaza, 1987 October 26; 5 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
      - Interviews with Madeleine Lejwa, 1977-1982; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
      - Poetry Reading, circa 1970s-1980s; 7 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
      - "Project for Aubette", circa 1970s; 2 sound tape reels (Box 21)
      - Public Lecture by Madeleine Lejwa, 1977 July 13; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Bill, Jerusalem, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 21)
    - Max Bill, Jerusalem Installation, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Compilation tape of "Chronicle of the Dead" (1946), Review of "Experiment E" by Peter Lind (1949), and Dr. Arthur Lejwa's "The Doctor Discovers" (1945), 1994; 4 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Dada Recordings, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Dadaists Kurt Schwitters, Raoul Hausmann, undated; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Fangor Review of Show, undated; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
    - Feigel and Vacossin, "Sog der Wellen", undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Hong Kong, China trip, 1987; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Interview with Burgoyne Diller and Bill Seitz, by Irving Sandler, undated; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
    - Interview with Marcel Duchamp, by Richard Hamilton, 1975; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Interview with Lebenstein, undated; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
    - Interview with Gabrielle Picabia, Paris France, 1978; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Israel Epstein, Beijing, 1987; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Lecture by Ira Spear, "Aboard the Argonaut", 1982; 2 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Arthur Lejwa and Leon (Chalette) Voice, undated; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
    - "Les Mains Regardent" Catalogue, Centre Pompidou, undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Kyoto, 1987; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - "Our Visit to Israel", undated; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Tokyo Synagogue, Shanghai, 1987; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Unlabeled Tapes, circa 1960s; 3 Sound cassettes (Box 21)
    - Vasalery Exhibit, 1964; 1 sound tape reels (Box 21)
    - Washington, 1991 February 22; 2 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 21)
  - Film and Video Recordings, circa 1950s-1995; 8.2
    This subseries contains 54 film reels (Super 8 mm), 4 film reels (16 mm), and 7 videocassettes (VHS). Recordings are related to artists, exhibits, and installations, as well as Madeleine Lejwa's personal interests. The subseries also includes a French film made for television, "Jean Arp or the Enigmatic Swimmer," circa 1966, as well as the printed synopsis and translation of the film. The folder titles are based on the labeling of the recorded media. Other than the previously described Arp film, there are no transcripts of the film recordings. The folders are arranged alphabetically by subject or last name. Film reels are Super 8 mm unless otherwise indicated.
    - Jean Arp (Box 22)
      - "Jean Arp or the Enigmatic Swimmer", circa 1966; 2 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Exhibit at Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1972; 1 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 2)
      - Miscellaneous, 1976; 3 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 3)
      - "Project for Aubette", circa 1970s; 2 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - San Francisco, circa 1970s; 3 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Sculptures and Arp Installation, circa 1970s; 1 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Sightseeing with Marguerite, 1971; 1 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Australia, circa 1970s; 2 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Israel, 1967-1975; 12 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 9-10)
    - Kennedy Center Award, Alvin Nicolais (Alwin Nikolais), 1988; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - Mendon Studios, undated; 2 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-1970s; 7 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 13-14)
    - Miscellaneous, Personal, 1971, 1979; 2 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - Museums and Exhibits, undated; 5 Film reels (Box 22, Folder 16-17)
    - Rabin Funeral, 1995; 3 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Richey, circa 1970s; 1 Film reels (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Sound Test Reels, undated; 5 Film reels (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
    - Steven Solarz on Eyewitness News, November 1992; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Vasarely, circa 1970s; 6 Film reels (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
    - Venice Bienale, 1968; 3 Film reels (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Oversized Film Reels, circa 1966 (Box 26, Folder 1)
      Oversized reels from Box 22, Folder 1.